<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vvorthy vvorke profitable to this whole kingdome Concerning the mending of all high-waies, as also for waters and iron workes. By Tho: Procter Esquire.</title>
            <author>Procter, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10145</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20400</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115291</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850510</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850510</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15718</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10145)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15718)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 723:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vvorthy vvorke profitable to this whole kingdome Concerning the mending of all high-waies, as also for waters and iron workes. By Tho: Procter Esquire.</title>
                  <author>Procter, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Allde &amp; are to be sold at his house on Lambard-hill, neere Olde-fish-streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A description of mending highwaies.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Roads --  Design and construction --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Roads --  Maintenance and repair --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15718:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15718:1"/>
            <p>A WORTHY vvorke Profitable to this whole kingdome.</p>
            <p>Concerning the mending of all high-waies, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for waters and Iron workes.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Tho: Procter</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by E. Allde &amp; are to be ſold at his houſe on Lambard-hill, neere Olde-fiſh-ſtreete. 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15718:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15718:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To his moſte excellent Maieſtie</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe proiects of the Author.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y knowledge true I did preferre,</l>
               <l>vnto your highneſse proiects three</l>
               <l>Of mickle worth, exceeding farre</l>
               <l>the ſubtill ſleight of Enmitie.</l>
               <l>Shee ſeekes my truth for to ſuppreſſe,</l>
               <l>And I to Wiſdome for redreſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where reaſon is by knowledge found,</l>
               <l>your highneſſe pleaſure to fulfill:</l>
               <l>Extending many a thouſand pound,</l>
               <l>in ſecret knowne to Arte and skill,</l>
               <l>Should ſingle wits thereiudge or deeme</l>
               <l>where knowledge wants or hath not beene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I am not of that learned lore,</l>
               <l>of <hi>Riplie, Kellie,</hi> and other moe;</l>
               <l>Whoſe learned worke<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are gone before,</l>
               <l>figuratiuely, Imeane not ſo,</l>
               <l>But plainely in a homely ſtile,</l>
               <l>ſhewing the truth deuoide of guile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In plow-mans painefull toile,</l>
               <l>my skill is ſomething good:</l>
               <l>And in the arte deuoide of guile,</l>
               <l>my minde not wauering stood.</l>
               <l>Loe yet my heart could not diſcearne,</l>
               <l>by gloſing wordes that skill to learne.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:15718:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:15718:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:15718:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>By duety I doe bow and yeelde,</l>
               <l>by rigors rage I nothing ſee:</l>
               <l>By guilefull guiftes that hath been ſild,</l>
               <l>brought to the baites of flatterie:</l>
               <l>My ſight not dim, though blinde I am,</l>
               <l>and liues on earth a ſimple man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I am not knowne, nor will not be,</l>
               <l>but as the Bird who ſeeth the net:</l>
               <l>I fall into each ieopardie,</l>
               <l>and none but God the ſame can let,</l>
               <l>Therefore good King know moſt iuſt,</l>
               <l>in God aboue I put my truſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For if with golde I had beene fedde,</l>
               <l>my ſellfe had had a paſsing parte:</l>
               <l>And eke my ſences had been led,</l>
               <l>from learning of that noble arte</l>
               <l>Of knowledge, which ſo many knowe,</l>
               <l>vnto the end it proues not ſo,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For knowledge is a ſccret thing,</l>
               <l>and knowledge is a vertue great:</l>
               <l>And knowledge doth make wiſdome ſpring</l>
               <l>and knowledge tis wherof we treate.</l>
               <l>The loue and life of euerie thing,</l>
               <l>with due obedience to our King.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bliſſe-full thy hap, thy life, and eke the daies,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>as <hi>Dauid</hi> did to God, giue thou thy praiſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who was, who is, euerlaſting ſeeing,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rules Princes dead, and thoſe now aliue being.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15718:4"/>
            <head>A Deſcription of the manner how to <hi>mend high-waies.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Treatiſe &amp; diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of High wayes, for theſe partes of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Kingdome of <hi>Greate Brittaine,</hi> with their diuers and ſeuerall plat-formes, frames, order, and manner of making of them, whereby all the ſaid high-waies ſhall or may bee made more ſound and ſtrong, pleaſant, and comfortable for all maner of way-faring iourneying, or traueling with Cartes and carriages, or other waies by theſe ſaid highwaies, All which is heerein plainely laide open and made manifeſt by <hi>Thomas Proctor</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. In this his Treatiſe is ſet downe for the generall good and helpfull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of al Countrime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; for al places, and chiefly and moſte needefully, where
<pb facs="tcp:15718:5"/>there is greate lacke and want of good waies, and where there are verie little or no good waies made: as in <hi>Holland</hi> in <hi>Lincolne-ſhire</hi> &amp; ſuch like: and to the dayly continuall great griefe and heart break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of man and beaſt, with charges, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drances, wearing and tyring of them, and ſometime to the great and imminent danger of their liues, and ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpoile and loſſe of goods, and alſo in ſome places elſe where, great hurt and ſpoile of Fences and groundes, with riding and going o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Corne, and ſuch like, by ſhifting &amp; ſeeking the beſt way diuerſly: all which by theſe meanes are, or may bee remedied and preuented: And although it may be that in the foreſaid places, or ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there hath beene beſtowed the yearelye great allowance of ſo many yeares paſt, with the yearelye labours and charges thereof, and thereto by the lawes appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and prouided with the beneuolence of ſo many well diſpoſed perſons, deſcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which haue giuen for and towardes the making, mending, and repayring of high waies, in diuers and ſundrie places of this his Maieſties ſaide kingdome,
<pb facs="tcp:15718:5"/>with diuers other voluntarie helpes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the ſaide greate allowance of men, and matter fitting to theſe yearelye and common daies labour and workes, &amp;c. The aforeſaid conſiderately looked into, he findeth no reaſon why there ſhould be any ill waies. Notwithſtanding, all which, or much therof hath been beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to little or no purpoſe, but much there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of vtterly loſt both coſt, worke and ſtuffe, for want of meete matter, or orderly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in diſpoſing the ſame in their ſaide workes, as appeares too manifeſtlye in moſte of thoſe their works at this day. And as he by his practiſe and coſts, hath found true and prooued: That the labour of twentie fixe able perſons, that are readie in their worke, and well diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thereunto with Pick-are, ſpade ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, rake and rammer, chipaxe and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gur, to be choſen and taken out of euerie pariſh, and ſo forth generallye out of all ſuch numbers, of all vſuall and common daies labours, &amp;c. Orderlye to bee ſet to worke in this his manner, with their carts &amp; carriages according, with ſome boyes and maides to helpe, where cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:15718:6"/>requires, ſhal or may ſuffice to make half a furlong yearelye, and as much good and faire way, and diſpatch them, to the bettering of the worſt and fouleſt waies to be made good and ſtrong in euerie pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, as twice ſo manye ſhould or could haue done heeretofore in this proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned worke and orderly manner without this ſaide preſcribed manner and order heerein made knowne. And heere withal is to be remembred that one principal and chiefe cauſe of al bad and foule waies is, that the raine water or other water doth lye and reſt vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> highwaies (not order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and ſoundlye made) which with the working of cart wheeles &amp; others, dooth peirce downe more deeper into the ſaide waies, and ſo more and more doth ſoften and rot the ſame, as by dayly experience is ſeene and knowne. And alſo that the ditches and common ſhowers are not yearely clenſed ſo as is needfull, which are the beſt helpes to drawe and dreane the waters off and from the moſte parte of all highwaies and groundes (as in reaſon there ſhould bee) and by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſties lawes ought to bee done; which
<pb facs="tcp:15718:6"/>not hauing beene done orderly is one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of, and wherby much of their former labours and charges with their waies and works are waſted, as aforeſaid, and little good way to bee found, whereas theſe foreſaid thinges otherwiſe preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then once well made and ſtronglye done, though but a furlong yearelye in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie pariſh ſo to bee made, ſo as one pariſh may bee helpfull vnto another next adioyning with men or mony, of the ſurpulſages of other greater pariſhes, to ſupplie the wantes of the leſſer pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, at the rate heere in this his book ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed ſo as by help one of another, there may eaſilye bee performed yearelye fortie rodds at the leaſt in euerie pariſh, and ſo yearely by little and little heereby all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer labours &amp; charges which haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitably beene waſted, ſhall bee cut off, and all ſuch future labours and charges ſhal be preuented and ſaued to ſome need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and profitable vſes: For this ſaide worke once well made and done, muſt needes be better and cheaper, then yerely ſtill a making and doing, and neuer well made and done, ſo as it ought to bee, and
<pb facs="tcp:15718:7"/>as is by the lawes therfore appointed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and ment.</p>
            <p>The neglect and neceſſitie wherof, and the loue to his country in this his laſt age and yeares, hath inforced him hereunto, out of his care, charge, paines and pract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice, to make known the ſame. The effects whereof dooth and may appeare with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his ſtudies &amp; labours for the general good of all in this his booke duelye or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently conſidered, to the making and bettering, as is aforeſaide of all high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, thereby to be made more ſufficient and durable, more eaſie, with much leſſer matter, ſtuffe, charges, and expences the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer heeretofore hath beene done (by their common daies labors) which by Art and action dooing, wil &amp; may cut off and ſaue very much of the yerely charges &amp; labors of former times and works, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Firſt therfore a platforme and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt bee caſt &amp; made in cawſy-wiſe, that is to ſay, to be made a rodd broad at the leaſt, wherupon two carts may meet and paſſe one by another, &amp; on either ſide the ſaid cawſie of that bredſh, to draw a ditch of <hi>3.</hi> foot depth, &amp; <hi>4.</hi> foot broad, &amp; that
<pb facs="tcp:15718:7"/>earth which ſhal be ſo digged, muſt be caſt vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſaid ditch to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> midſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of a rod broad, proportionally, that the middeſt &amp; height of the ſaid way may bee in bredth one yard, &amp; higher by two foote in the midſt, then at the outward ſides or edges of the ſame: the higher y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> midſt and lower the ſides, the drier and better way to void the water, which water is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rotting and ſpoyling of al high waies, and the only loſſe of al charge and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon daies labours heretofore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no good way hath been made and continued for want of true maner and forme, and due conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration hereof in their former works.</p>
            <p>Secondly this cawſie, if it be of a clayiſh ſoile, or of ſuch like ſlimy or ſpungy earth, it muſt be wrought and caſt vp in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeaſon, that it may haue time to ſettle and ioyne firmly and ſoundly together, &amp; ſo being caſt and made as before ſaid, that no carts be ſuffered to paſſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, til the ſpring time, or that the earth thereof bee drie and hard, for marring and breaking his ſhape and forme made as before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide, for if in Summer it ſhall bee caſte, it wil riſe in ſuch hard clottes and
<pb facs="tcp:15718:8"/>tough greate lumpes, as will hardlye with greate labour and much ramming bee diſgeſted and brought to a good foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, but at a far more greater charge then the before ſaid, when the earth is ſoft and kindely to digge and ioyne together.</p>
            <p>The which thus caſt &amp; made in winter as before, beſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that your forenamed ditches on either ſide the ſaide Cawſie be ſo artificially and hanſomelye contriued, made and clenſed of filth and ſoile, that the raine water which ſhall fall from the ſaid Cawſie, may haue a ſpeedie Current in thoſe ditches, and ſo falling into ditch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es which muſt bee made by ſome good iudgement of workemen, or other inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to that purpoſe, that the ſaid water from thence may haue a good and ſpeedy paſſage to the next ditches, and ſo from ditch to ditch, gutter to gutter, or other conueyances of water to the common ſhoares, and ſo to the next brook or maine ſtreame adioyning to the ſaide workes or any of them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if your ground or earth in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of your waies to be made, bee garden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like moulde, ſoft, ſandye or crumbling, or
<pb facs="tcp:15718:8"/>ſuch like ſhort earth, then will that ſort of earth with ſmall labour of ramming of it ſelfe, with treading and going vpon it in their labours &amp; workes, ſettle and ioyne ſoundly together, and eſpeciallye after ſome good ſhewres of raine falne there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, which then will be a good founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion preſently, to frame and binde in with Timber, woodrailes or powles, as to place, lay, fill, and couer with ſtones gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, ſand, or ſmall wood to be cut of Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let or faggot faſhion, or anye other hard or drie matter to bee had or made by art or otherwiſe (according to the plentie or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of euerie ſoile and place) as in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and in euerie ſundrie ſeueral man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſorts &amp; formes of works and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, in this his booke is declared, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and plainely ſet downe in their places for euerie one to follow and worke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after accordingly: al which manners and emptie places of all thoſe wood frames you do vſe, muſt be filled as you ſee, either with wood, ſtones, Iron-cinders, Iron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones, Geauel ſtones or other, &amp; ſo filled. Laſtly to be well couered ouer with ſmal grauel, rubbiſh or ſand, or anye other
<pb facs="tcp:15718:9"/>ſtones broken ſmal. And heere is to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that in euery pariſh one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other there are to be eſtimated of vnſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keable or vnknown numbers of houſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders plowes &amp; carts to be rated at three ſhillings euery cart, and therfore ſo many men for their worke of highwaies, to bee rated but at <hi>8.</hi> pence euerie man the day, beſides the help of women and children, fit to ſerue in this worke as heeretofore haue done, for gathering of ſtones and carrying of matter and ſtuffes with bowles, creeles and baskets &amp; ſuch like, for to fil hollow places according to their accuſtomed &amp; yerely vſual maner heereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in repayring of high waies, which yerely amounteth to a great ſumme.</p>
            <p>From amongſt which numbers of houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, plowes and carts before ſaid are to be choſen or made for this worke two and fiftie men, with <hi>12.</hi> carts, and <hi>12</hi> men part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid <hi>52.</hi> for the ſeruice of <hi>6.</hi> daies to bring in matter and ſtuffe likewiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtom of the yerely repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of high waies in euerye pariſhe, and that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery cart &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ſeruiceable in theſe workes, to be rated for their <hi>6.</hi> daies
<pb facs="tcp:15718:9"/>labour, but as aforeſaide, after three ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges the day for euerye cart ſo ſeruing, and the reſt of the ſaid labouring men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>38</hi> to be rated as aforeſaid after eight pence the day, of which number of <hi>38.</hi> there muſt be <hi>20</hi> at the leaſt of verie ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient able men of ſome good iudgement in their own labours: If ſuch bee wanting they muſt be choſen and hired to doe ſuch work as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſurueyor or ſurueyors of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid work, ſhal direct &amp; appoint in euery pariſh according to theſe his rules in this his book vnder writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Likewiſe out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid reſt of <hi>52.</hi> now remaining, being now but <hi>20.12.</hi> muſt be ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t laborers with ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, pickare and ſpades, for making and fitting the ſaide platforme and foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in manner and forme (as before ſaid) to be readie for the ſecond work, to be laid, made and framed vpon, to bee filled with earth, and faſt rammed for ſhrinking.</p>
            <p>Theſe laſt before ſaid, <hi>20.</hi> ſuch able men wil digge ditch, caſt, leuell, plaine, and make readie, and finiſh fortie rods, which is a furlong in all the ſaide ſire daies, according to the Statutes heeretofore made, of and for the workes of euerye
<pb facs="tcp:15718:10"/>yeare for euerie pariſh yearely this work during, but ſeauen or tenn yeares ſpace, which after the ſaide accompt of fortie roddes in euerie pariſh yearely to bee wrought and made as before ſaide; will make good, fil, and dry vp al foule, hollow &amp; bad places with a ſmall yerelye charge and labour to bee maintained, paſſable, good and faire for euer after, where here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore the labours and coſts of ſuch great numbers of houſholders plowes &amp; carts for theſe fiftie yeres paſt haue beene ſpent and loſte, and little or fewe good waies made in any ſuch order, maner and forme.</p>
            <p>If the ground, ſoyle, or earth bee clay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, or deſtitute of ſtones, a binding muſt needes bee made for this worke of wood, framed and made &amp; likewiſe filled with wood, as appeareth by the platformes heareafter diſcribed: That is to ſay, poles of young wood, or rayles of baſe Timber, of length eighteene foote, and in thickneſſe or compaſſe round about ſome ten or twelue inches one with another, or leſſe where wood is ſcant, &amp; if they ſhall lacke of that length, to take two ſhorte, to make one longe, ſo as when they are fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:15718:10"/>and made fit, and pinned down with ſtakes with wodden pins through them, they may be a rod ſquare at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſaid frame and croſt with ſuch like timber made faſt as is needfull, according to the platformes and ſundrie maners of workes and working in this his booke plainely ſet downe.</p>
            <p>Alſo it is to bee conſidered, that if anye ſuch matter &amp; ſtuffe fit for the ſaid work, cannot bee had within two miles of the ſaid worke, as is moſte commonly to bee had within that compaſſe in moſt places &amp; pariſhes therabouts, being diligently ſought for, yet neuertheles <hi>12.</hi> cartes will ſuffice within their ſixe common daies la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, at two miles off, to bring in ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent loades of ſuch matterof ſtones, wood, or other drye or hard matter, as will performe the yearely accompliſhment and finiſhing of one furlong of the worſt way euerie yeare in euerie pariſh, being fortie rods a yeare: and if it be at a mile off, or from the worke, then ſixe cartes will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme as much as the other twelue: if but at halfe a mile from the ſaide workes or Cawſie, then three cartes are able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb facs="tcp:15718:11"/>the ſaide carriages, as in ſtonye or wood countries, where ſuch ſtuffes or ſtones are neare at hand. And then there &amp; in ſuch places, ſo much money, labours &amp; charges is ſpared &amp; gotten after three ſhillings in euerie cart by day, more then in other pariſhes, where it is not ſo eaſie to be had, and ſo likewiſe in the mens la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors of euery houſholder after eight pence by day, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taining great numbers in their former labours of their ſaid high-waies, beſides women &amp; children, as aforeſaid, yerely heeretofore ſo inconſiderntely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed and ſpent: all which charges heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſo ſaued, ſome part thereof to bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed and reckoned for wood for the ſaid frames and ſtrong binding, and making of the ſaid cawſie and high-waies with their belongings, &amp; all the reſt ſo ſaued to bee at his Maieſties good pleaſure, to whoſe moſt gratious fauour, hee humbly ſubmitteth himſelfe, and to the good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of all his louing countrie men, for this his skill and paines taken ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly to his coſt and charge in ſetting foorth this his manners of high waies, with his other proiects of water, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:15718:11"/>of anye drie towne to haue waters brought vnto them, or neare vnto them, or bringing one riuer to or neare vnto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as Thames to or neare Seuerne, or Seuerne neare or to Thames at an eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er rate then any other, for botes, lighters and bardges with their ladings and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages to paſſe too and froe with Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coales, which are as wel in his maieſties forreſt of <hi>Deane</hi> as in Wales, are plentie to be had neare there abouts, for tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at a reaſonable rate, with other more ſuch like places (as now from New-caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le in way of Decaye) and alſo for making of Iron in quality and quanty good and merchantable, according to the nature of the mine, with a third part of wood-coles wher it may be ſpared, or otherwiſe with out any wood coles at al at greate profit, ſuch as thereon may bee gained, <hi>33.</hi> ſhillings vpon euery tunne, as the priſe of Iron there now goeth, or three ſhillings vppon twentie, vpon euerie returne where the ſame ſhall bee made, for the generall good of his maieſties kingdome and Subiects.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15718:12"/>
            <p>All which, or any of them, he ſhall ſhew &amp; performe the tryall by actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; working of workemen, with cleare appearance of the benefits and profits theron, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to his Maieſtie if hee ſhall be called thereto, and thence to any other that ſhal deſire to be ſatisfied therein, that ſhall bee fit and furniſhed therefore.</p>
            <p>A tryall and true performance of all the before ſaid, may bee made vnder ſixtie pound expences fully to ſatiffie, euery one of capable vnderſtanding.
<q>
                  <l>Theſe being true, as true they be,</l>
                  <l>not ſet to worke is great pittie,</l>
                  <l>But ſcorne and blame ſuch workes they haue,</l>
                  <l>where enuie knowledge doth depraue.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15718:12"/>
Theſe frames heereafter following (beeing made of Wood) doe repreſent euerie one of them a rodde of ground ſquare, where they ſhall bee made in wood countries, and where there is wood to be had, may all of them, or any of them be filled with wood, cut billet or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got faſhion, with hurdles or wattles, with bauins or bruſh wood, or ſuch like for want of bigger, being vnbound and well placed and laid, and then well coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ouer with other matter, &amp; in manner as is declared with ſmall grauell, or gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell ſtones broken ſmall, Iron-ſtone, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron Cinders, ſandie ſtone, thalke or lime, or any other hard or drie matter, made by art out of killnes: as bricke, hard tile, Potſhardes or other earth, ſand or any rubbiſh whatſoeuer: the dryer, harder, and ſmaller, the better and fayrer the way will be.
<pb facs="tcp:15718:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:15718:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:15718:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:15718:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15718:15"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram of roadbed structure</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>diagram of section of roadbed structure</figDesc>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>diagram of section of roadbed structure</figDesc>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram of roadbed structure with wood, stone, etc. fillers</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>diagram of section of roadbed structure with wood, stone, etc. fillers</figDesc>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>diagram of roadbed structure with wood, stone, etc. fillers</figDesc>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:15718:16"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of wattle framework</figDesc>
               <p>Theſe are to be likened to the ſheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold hurdles, and foure of theſe will ſerue a rodde way.</p>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram of crossed framework forming part of roadbed</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>diagram of x-crossed framework filled with stones</figDesc>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram of latticed framework forming part of roadbed structure</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>diagram of latticed framework filled with stones</figDesc>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram of latticed framework forming part of roadbed structure</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <p>This middeſt and height of the way thus bound, may be filled with any drie matter.</p>
                              <figDesc>diagram of latticed framework filled with stones</figDesc>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>dioagram of latticed framework forming part of roadbed structure</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>diagram of latticed framework filled with stones</figDesc>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram of framework filled with paving stones, forming part of roadbed</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>diagram of framework filled with paving stones</figDesc>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram of wattled frameword forming part of roadbed</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>diagram of part of wattled framework</figDesc>
                              <p>This is the middeſt and height of the waies, being left a yarde and a halfe broad, filled and couered with any <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                                    <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                 </gap> matter</p>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of ditch bordering roadbed</figDesc>
                              <head>Ditch</head>
                           </figure>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <p>This about of hurdles is an eaſie, ſtrong, and cheap way, and is good for clayiſh or ſpungie groundes or any other.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15718:18"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram of framework for roadbed</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>And laſtly in thoſe Countries and places, where there ſhall lacke, and is not, or cannot be found, ſtones, grauell, ſand, or young ſpring wood, to make frames, and to be cut billet or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got faſhion, neither Iron cinders, or anye ſuch like hard and drie matter to fill and couer therwith, as in <hi>Holland</hi> in Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colnoſhire and ſuch other. That there, and in ſuch places, they muſt make or cauſe to be made, kilnes like lime kilnes, brick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kilnes,
<pb facs="tcp:15718:18"/>Tile, or Potter kilnes, wherein they muſt burne with ſea-coales, pets or Turnes, claye or earth, &amp; make hard matter thereof, of hardneſſe poterlike: the bigger of which matter ſhall make the vpper part of the way vppon the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation therof, and the ſmaller thereof to couer againe vper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte aboue the other greater before ſaid, and ſo ramme and ſettle the ſame cloſe together on their high-waies there &amp; in ſuch places, where their greateſt care in their workes muſt be to leaue their waies high in the midſt, and ſo euen and han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, that no raine-water or ouerflowinges ſhall tarrie or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their cawſie or high waies, but fal ſpeedily into their ditches, as is moſte meets and preſcribed to all high waies, and in theſe places, and in ſuch like, where there is little wood or none to bee had for heipe thereof, it ſhall bee verie good and profitable that there the inhabitants or dwellers neare, or other waies ſhall plant &amp; ſet young plants of willowes or other, as ſhall bee moſt meete or fitting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, al along by the ſides of the ſaid high-waies and ditches, which will growe and yeelde in ſhort time, yearely helpe to the mending &amp; repayring of the ſame ſaid high waies, wattles and with hurdles.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The benefits and profits that ſhall or may ariſe vnto his Maieſtie and ſubiects, here by art and action doing, if ſet on worke accordingly.</head>
               <p>HIs Maieſtie by his moſte royall authority, and there vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this preſcribed manner to bee performed and done. There ſhall be good &amp; faire wayes made, which ſince the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of ſuch good lawes, hetherto theſe 50. yeres paſt &amp; more, hath not beene made and done accordingly, ſo as is now here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by taught and ſet foorth how to bre done, and moſte of them may be finiſhed within the time preſcribed, or thereabouts: where by from hencefoorth may bee faued manye thouſand loades of matter and ſtuffe, charges and labors, and ſo thethy and there through many thouſands of pounds yereiy, If but rated after three ſhillings for euerie Cart, out of ſuch num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers as are ſet uſceable to this ſaid worke, by his Maiſties Lawes and ſtatutes appointed. And likewiſe, if but after <hi>8.</hi> pence the day for euery man, out of the aforeſaid greate num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb facs="tcp:15718:19"/>ſo ſeruiceable as before ſaid, &amp; yet notwithſtanding ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient left for the yerely repayring of the ſaid waies for euer, and the reſt ſo ſaued whatſoeuer, may be otherwiſe neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imployed to other vſes according to his maieſties good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or as ſhall be found moſt meete by his maieſtie, and his moſte honorable priuie counſell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Alſo for waters, Riuers and their benefits.</head>
               <p>THeſe ſaide waters or ſmall riuers made for Boates and lighters to paſſe, that is to ſay, from one riuer to or neare vnto another, or from one Cittie, towne or place, too or neare vnto another, or into one another, where the ſame ſhall bee found meete and needfull: as from Thames too or neare vnto Seuerne, or from Seuerne to or neare vnto Thames, as alſo from <hi>Sarisburie, Stampford, North-hampton, Berry, Wak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> and <hi>Leedes,</hi> or <hi>Oxford,</hi> as alſo from the riuer of <hi>Lee,</hi> neare vnto <hi>Stock-bridge,</hi> to or neare vnto <hi>Clarken-well</hi> lying, and being on the north ſide of London: all which or any of them may be done accordingly, and any of the which he wil vndertake to doe at an caſterate, and better cheape then anye other ſhall doe, not vſing his way and manner. For that hee ſeeth in other mens workes, labors and manner, much vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably ſpent, which may and might be ſpaced and ſaued, all which the generall and neceſſarie vſes whereof are many: as for tranſportation and carrying of coales, Sea-coales, wood, Leade, Iron, corne and graine, Flaxe, Hempe, Wollen and Linnen cloath, with many diuers and ſundrie commodities, whereby a cuſtome or rent may growe vnto his Maieſty, and caſe of charges &amp; benefit by charges, &amp; other benefits by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of commodities to diuere Townes, ſhires and places, whereby men euerie where may be ſtirred vp and prouoked diuerſly to ſeeke and finde out ſuch commodities whatſoeuer their Countrie ſhall affoord and bring foorth to the proffiting of themſelues and others, And alſo by this meanes, that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried for fiue ſhillings, which now vpon euerie tunne carrying coſteth twentie, which then there ſhall or may be ſaued to help them vpon their commodities. The greatnes of the manifolde benefits, that heereby ſhall, may or might growe, hee leaueth to the good conſideration and profound iudgement of the beſt
<pb facs="tcp:15718:19"/>and wiſeſt, &amp; to the good vnderſtanding of all in generall. The ſaid riuers or ſtreames whereſoeuer, to be made a rodde or pearch broad at the leaſt, at 250. pound a mile, or better cheape, as before ſaid: not offending, impeaching, or hurting Milles, dammes, weares or ſtreames or fiſhings, neither o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerflowing any mans grounds otherwiſe then their ordinary courſes or paſſadges, but rather bettering thoſe mens grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds diuers waies, thorow which the ſaid waters ſhal paſſe, to the multiplying of water to the ſaid Mils and groundes in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, &amp; in drie places and ſeaſons, &amp; multiplying of fiſh &amp; foule: and vpon agreement or reaſonable requeſte made, he ſhal and wil be readie with one of his Sonnes, named <hi>Elias Procter,</hi> of good &amp; ſuffictent ſkil, &amp; experience in the ſaid works, or one of them, vpon ſome conuenient warning giuen, or procurement before made, to come &amp; to ſhew &amp; make and ſet foorth the ſaide water courſes, or paſſages, or any of them, for the better ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rod by rod, how &amp; which way y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſhal or may be done, whereby the owners thorow whoſe grounds y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſhal paſſe may be agreed &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pounded with therfore, yeelding him or them but reaſonable &amp; neceſſary charges for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, their man &amp; horſes for their comming &amp; going for ſome 15. daies or therabouts, as ſhal be found but meet and reaſonable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Theſe hereunder doth declare &amp; make known the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits &amp; profits that ſhal or may ariſe vpon the making of yron, if the ſame ſhal be made with &amp; after the direction of the ſaid Author in act &amp; action, with true performance accordingly.</head>
               <p>FIrſt to make Iron with a third part of wood-coales, where ſpring woods are, and may be ſpared for the benefit of the owners, or elſe to make Iron without any wood-coales at all, where there ſhall ariſe profit vpon the work And making of good and vſuall marchantable Iron, according to the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the mettle of the mine there, to euerie one, or to any one that ſhall lay in and imploy ſtocke and money thereon to all needfull and neceſſarie vſes fit and meete for the ſame, vpon the returne of euerie tunne ſo made, 20. ſhillings: or three ſhillinges vpon the returne of euerie twentie ſhillings ſo wrought and made into Iron, as before ſaide, of cleare profit, after the rate as the ordinarie price of Iron there now goeth, where the ſame Iron ſhall bee made or wrought, and ſo much Iron weekelye there to be made, wrought and laide by, to bee deliuered orderlye to ſecure and benefitte the ſaid ſtocke and worke, weekely after that rate, and to counteruaile, free, and diſcharge all other the ordinarie weekely charges, that ſhall bee imployed &amp; diſpenſed therein, with the profitt thereof and thereunto due, and ſo foorth from weeke to weeke from time to time foorth and forwards according: the ſaid ſtocke ſo continued, and the worke ſtill retuned, and going forwards. And ſo hee ſhall performe vnto the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de worke and profit yearelye the ſame <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> yearely of ſuch bar yron.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:15718:20"/>
               <head>To his Maieſtie for Farme or Rent.</head>
               <p>Where any ſuch worke ſhall be builded, erected, and ſet vp vpon his maieſties waſte lands or commons, with water and water courſes, Fuell, and Iron-ſtone, and for peate and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſaries fitting thereunto, to make rawe-Iron, bare-Iron, as is ſaide, and for farme rent twentie pound a yeare, yearely for the ſaid farme, whereas now there is ſcantly anye thing at all to bee had or made thereof: and likewiſe to euerie Lord or owner for farme, as beforeſaid vnto his Maieſtie <hi>20.</hi> pound the yeare for ſuch like farme and neceſſaries, where now there is ſcantly rayſed any rent thereof at al. And laſtlye the Author, explainer and maiſter of theſe his proiects, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and eſteemeth himſelfe worthie vpon performance of the ſurpluſage whatſoeuer of the profits of this his proiect ouer &amp; aboue as aforeſaid, or ſome certaine yearely ſtipend as ſhal be thought reaſonable therfore, and what other impoſition, bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and profits may heareby grow &amp; enſue to his maieſtyes kingdome and Subiects, humbly ſubmitteth himſelfe and all the reſt to the iudgement and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the beſt and moſte worthyeſt to conſure and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15718:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
